Beach, Webster, and Dickinson families papers
Litchfield Historical Society
Beach, Webster, and Dickinson families papers
1797-1990
Litchfield Historical Society 7 South Street, P.O. Box 385 Litchfield, CT, 6759 URL: http://www.litchfieldhistoricalsociety.org/archon Email: archivist@litchfieldhistoricalsociety.org Phone: 860-567-4501 Fax: 860-567-3565
Rice, Betsy Dickinson Dinan
Papers related to the Litchfield families of Beach, Webster, and Dickinson. In 1916, Bessie Rachel Beach (1893-1976) married Leonard Dickinson (1895-1946). The parents of Bessie were Milo D. Beach (1861-1959) and Louisa Webster Beach (1862-1951). The papers relate to these three family lines.
1995-15-0
Biographical Note
Betsy Dickinson Dinan Rice is the daughter of Bessie Beach Dickinson (1893-1976) and Leonard Dickinson (1895-1946) and granddaughter of Louisa Webster Beach (1862-1951) and Milo Beach (1861-1959).
Scope and Contents
Papers related to the Litchfield families of Beach, Webster, and Dickinson. In 1916, Bessie Rachel Beach (1893-1976) married Leonard Dickinson (1895-1946). The parents of Bessie were Milo D. Beach (1861-1959) and Louisa Webster Beach (1862-1951). The papers relate to these three family lines.
The Beach, Webster, and Dickinson families have a long history in Litchfield and all settled there in the 1700s. The Websters of Litchfield are distant relatives of Noah Webster, as they all descended from the same ancestor who first came to America in the 1600s. The Dickinson line is related to noted miniature painter Anson Dickinson, as it descended from one of Anson's brothers. There is no relation to the poet Emily Dickinson.
Milo D. Beach operated the Litchfield Creamery from 1900 to 1940. At the time it closed, it was the last creamery in Connecticut. Bessie Beach Dickinson was a long-time piano teacher and organist for the First Congregational Church. Leonard Dickinson worked at the creamery until opening Dickinson's Dairy-Maid, a tea-room specializing in homemade ice cream, in the mid 1930s. The papers do not document the business activities of the families.
A large part of the collection consists of genealogical information culled from a variety of sources. Original materials include marriage certificates; correspondence; mortgages and deeds; distribution and inventories of estates, scrapbooks; clippings; 19th century recipe ("receipt") books (one book is an account book from 1820s-1850s that has been pasted over); 19th and early 20th century newspapers and clippings, including the Litchfield Monitor (1802-1803), Litchfield Republican (1856), and Connecticut Courant (1820s); autograph albums; documentation on Goshen and Milton; many family photographs of various types, including daguerreotypes, tintypes, cartes-de-viste, and cabinet cards, also two large albums from the late 19th century photographs; and 19th and early 20th century books.
Arrangement of Materials
The collection is arranged in four series:
1. Beach/Webster family
2. Dickinson family
3. Photographs
4. Publications
Separated Materials
Objects have been removed to the museum collections.
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Litchfield Creamery
Family Name:
Beach family; Dickinson family; Webster family
Genre/Form of Material:
Account books; Autograph albums; Correspondence; Deeds; Diaries; Estate inventories; Marriage certificates; Mortgages; Photographs; Recipes; Scrapbooks
Geographic Name:
Goshen (Conn.); Litchfield (Conn.)
Personal Name:
Beach, Bessie Rachel; Beach, Louisa Webster; Beach, Milo D.; Dickinson, Leonard
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Litchfield Historical Society from Betsy Dickinson Dinan Rice on 12/05/1995.
Other Information
This collection was processed with support from the National Historical Publications and Records Commission (NHPRC).
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Beach/Webster family
  - Autograph book, 1879-1880 (Folder 1)
  - Beach, Heman estate, 1840 (Folder 2)
  - Beach, Milo D. account book, 1924-1945 (Folder 3)
    Lists his charitable contributions.
  - Beach/Webster genealogy (Folder 4)
    From blue binder. Primarily contains photocopies of materials found elsewhere in the collection.
  - Beach/Webster genealogy (Folder 5)
  - Brown, Bertha Bruner, "Some Pages of Family History", 1932 (Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, [?], Henry M. Civil War letter, 1962 Mar 18 (Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1931-1958 (Folder 8)
  - Documents, 1840-1856 (Folder 9)
  - Family record, 1800s-1900s (Folder 10)
  - Genealogical notes (Folder 11)
  - High school graduations, 1915, 1940 (Folder 12)
  - M. D. Beach pasteurized medium cream bottle stopper, circa 1900-1940 (Folder 13)
  - Merry Christmas Mother Dickinson, 1968 (Folder 14)
    Contains genealogical information.
  - Webster, Louisa autograph book, 1879-1899 (Folder 15)
  - Webster, Rachel Baldwin diary, 1876 (Folder 16)
  - Beach, Heman estate distribution, 1841 Apr 21
    Currently stored in box 10.
  - Deeds and related documents, 1823-1882
  - Deeds and related documents, "Part of Camp Dutton", 1820-1949
  - Newspapers
    19th and early 20th century newspapers and clippings, including the Litchfield Monitor (1802-1803), Litchfield Republican (1856), and Connecticut Courant (1820s). Currently stored in box 10.
- Dickinson family
  - The American Legion Magazine, 1964 Jul (Folder 1)
  - Buell, Jonathan estate survey, 1847 (Folder 2)
    Photocopy.
  - The Descendants of Thomas Beach of Milford, Connecticut, 1912 (Folder 3)
  - Diary extracts, anonymous, 1870-1907 (Folder 4)
  - Diary, anonymous, and notes and correspondence, 1900-1945 (Folder 5)
  - Dickinson, Bessie Beach correspondence, 1950-1969, undated (Folder 6)
  - Dickinson, Bessie Beach papers, circa 1950s, 1972 (Folder 7)
  - The Dickinson Genealogy (Folder 8)
  - Dickinson, Leonard cards, undated (Folder 9)
  - Dickinson, Leonard and Beach, Bessie marriage certificate, 1916 (Folder 10)
    Copy.
  - Dickinson, Minnie Brooker autograph book, 1883-1887 (Folder 11)
  - Dickinson, Minnie Brooker autograph book, 1884-1887 (Folder 12)
  - Genealogical materials (Folder 13)
  - Genealogical materials (Folder 14)
  - Genealogical materials (Folder 15)
  - Genealogical materials (Folder 16)
    From white binder.
  - The Genealogy Book for Sadie Hawley (Folder 17)
  - The Genealogy Book for Sadie Hawley, loose papers (Folder 18)
  - Gesner, Anthon Temple, The Dickinson Family of Milton and Litchfield, 1913 (Folder 19)
  - Pope, T. to Dickinson, Anson, 1816 Jun 4 (Folder 20)
  - Post cards, circa 1920s-1930s (Folder 21)
  - Programme of the Centennial Celebration of the Town of Goshen, 1876 (Folder 22)
  - Promissory note, 1797 (Folder 23)
  - Recipe book, early 1800s (Folder 24)
  - Recipe book, pasted over account book, 1820s-1830s (Folder 25)
  - The salt box house, circa 1930s (Folder 26)
  - Scrapbook, pasted in Annual Report of the Board of Education (1872), 1836-1930 (Folder 27)
  - Scrapbook, pasted in Report on Railroads (1891), 1874-1948 (Folder 28)
  - Scrapbook, Goshen and Goshen Methodist Church, circa 1890-1910 (Folder 29)
  - Scrapbook, Gossip from the Land of Goshen, circa 1890-1940 (Folder 30)
- Photographs
  - Beach/Webster family
    - Alling (Folder 1)
    - Barton (Folder 2)
    - Bates (Folder 3)
    - Beach (Folder 4)
    - Beach (Folder 5)
    - Beach (Folder 6)
    - Beach (Folder 7)
    - Beach (Folder 8)
    - Beach (Folder 9)
    - Beach (Folder 10)
    - Beach (Folder 11)
    - Fellows (Folder 12)
    - Gallup (Folder 13)
    - Krause (Folder 14)
    - Lufbery (Folder 15)
    - Mason (Folder 16)
    - Towle (Folder 17)
    - Webster (Folder 18)
    - Woodruff (Folder 19)
    - Album, "Presented to Grandma [from] Louie and Ruth", 1877 Jan
      Currently stored in box 8.
    - Oversize photographs
  - Dickinson family
    - Andrews (Folder 1)
    - Buell (Folder 2)
    - Dickenson (Folder 3)
    - Law (Folder 4)
    - Stoddard (Folder 5)
    - Thomas (Folder 6)
    - Wood (Folder 7)
    - Album, "To the memory of Sarah T. Dickinson"
      Currently stored in box 7.
    - Album, Louise Dickinson, cartes-de-viste
      Currently stored in box 9.
    - Oversize photographs
  - Other photographs
    - Bain (Folder 1)
    - Bell (Folder 2)
    - Mayer (Folder 3)
    - Scenes and views (Folder 4)
    - Unidentified people (Folder 5)
- Publications
  - All about Litchfield, 1959
  - Bulkeley, Historic Litchfield 1721-1907
  - Connecticut Historical Society, Annual report, 1968
  - Dearborn, Anson Dickinson, 1983
  - Goshen, Town of, Annual report, 1907
  - Hibbard, History of Goshen, 1897
  - A history of the First Congregational Church in Litchfield, Connecticut, 1955
  - An invitation to visit historic Litchfield Connecticut
  - Litchfield, Connecticut 250th anniversary, 1719-1969
  - Longfellow, Voices of the night, 1911
  - The Meetinghouse of the hill: the history of the First Congregational Church of Litchfield, Connecticut, 1971
  - The New-England galaxy, 1959 summer
  - New testament, 1865
    Inscribed by Louise Dickinson.
  - Old houses in and near Litchfield, Conn., 1961
  - Plymouth Chamber of Commerce, Plymouth, 1926
  - Plymouth visitor, circa 1965
  - Reunion of the Dickinson Family, at Amherst, Mass., 1884
  - Shepherd, Litchfield: portrait of a beautiful town..., 1969
  - Tales of Litchfield, undated
    Contemporary reprinting of 1933 articles.
  - Webster, A grammatical institute..., undated
    Contemporary reprinting.
  - White, A history of the town of Litchfield..., 1920
  - The White Memorial Foundation, 1938